<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thirty-five articles made and established by the rebells, the lords, and the rest of the Generall Assembly of that part of the kingdome of Ireland (now in rebellion) met at the citie of Kilkenny, Anno Dom. 1642</title>
            <author>Ireland. General Assembly at Kilkenny.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E246_36</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11309</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858991</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858991</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 42:E246[36])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Thirty-five articles made and established by the rebells, the lords, and the rest of the Generall Assembly of that part of the kingdome of Ireland (now in rebellion) met at the citie of Kilkenny, Anno Dom. 1642</title>
                  <author>Ireland. General Assembly at Kilkenny.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.P. and M.S. in Goldsmiths-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643. March the sixt.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Proclamations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>and commanded by the Malignant party, who are enemies to God our King, and his Majeſties well affected Subjects, this Aſſembly is neceſſitated during this warre, in ſome formalities and circumſtances, to deviate from the proceedings preſcribed by the ſaid Lawes and Statutes; Nevertheleſſe, reteining the ſubſtance and eſſence thereof, ſo far forth as the endleſſe malice and cruelty of their enemies the ſaid malignant party doth permit, who ſhut the ſaid places and other paſſages and wayes to his Majeſties juſtice and mercy, from his Majeſties well affected Subjects of this Kingdome. For the exaltation therefore of the holy Romane Catholique Church, for the advancement of his Majeſties ſervice, and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the lives, eſtates, and liberties of his Majeſties true Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, againſt the injuſtice, murthers, maſſacres, rapes, depredations, robberies, burnings, frequent breaches of publique faith and quarter, and deſtruction daily acted and perpetrated upon his Majeſties ſaid Subjects, and adviſed, contrived, and daily executed by the malignant party, ſome of them managing the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and affaires of State in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſome other parts of this Kingdome, to his Highnes great diſſervice, and complying with their confederates the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant party in <hi>England,</hi> and elſe-where, who as it is manifeſt to all the world, doe complot and practice to diſhonour and deſtroy his Majeſtie, his royall Conſort the Queene, their children, and Monarchicall Government; which is of moſt dangerous conſequence to all the Monarches and Princes of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The ſaid Aſſembly doth order and eſtabliſh a Counſell by the name of a Supreame Councell of the confederate Catholiques of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of the number of 24 to be forthwith named, ſhall reſide in this Citie, or where elſe within this Kingdome they ſhall thinke expedient, and the members of the ſaid Councell ſhall have equall votes; and two parts of 3. or more concurring, preſent votes to conclude, and no fewer to ſit in Counſell then 9. whereof 7. at leaſt are to concurre; and of the 24. a Preſident ſhall be named by this Aſſembly, who is to be one of the ſaid 12. reſident. And in caſe of his death, abſence, or ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the reſt of theſe who ſhall be reſident, may name a Vice-Preſident to the 24. And this Aſſembly is forthwith to name a Secretary and Clerk of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, the Secretary to be of the ſaid 24. And the Counſell ſhall have the power and preheminencies following; <hi>viz.</hi> The Lords, Generalls, and other Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Armies, and civill Magiſtrates, and Officers in the ſeverall Provinces ſhall obſerve their orders and decrees, and ſhall doe nothing contrary to theſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and ſhall give them ſpeedie advertiſements and account of their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and actions, with as much expedition as may be, that the ſaid Counſell ſhall have power to order and determine all ſuch matters as by this Aſſembly ſhall be left undetermined, and ſhall be recommended unto them. And their orders therein to be of force, untill the next Aſſembly, and after untill the ſame be revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. That the ſaid Counſell ſhall have power &amp; authoritie to queſtion and inflict condigne puniſhment upon all Commanders of Armies, exempted from the power of the Generalls, and upon the Generalls themſelves, and upon all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, Magiſtrates, and other perſons of what degree or qualitie ſoever; and upon any of themſelves in cauſes of delinquency.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> 6. That the ſaid Counſell ſhall have power and authoritie to doe and execute all manner of arts and things conducing to the advancement of the Catholique cauſe, and good of this Kingdome, and concerning this warre, as if done by this Aſſembly, and ſhall have power to heare and ordaine all matters capitall, crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, or civill, excepting the right or title of Land.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the Generalls or other Commanders of Armies, and all Governours and civill Magiſtrates, and all other perſons within this Realme, ſhall obey the orders and decrees of the ſaid Councell, touching the preſent ſervice: that the ſaid Counſell ſhall have for their Guard the number of 500. foot and 200. horſe, to be equally extracted out of the Armes of the foure Provinces. It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that in every Province of this Kingdome, there ſhall be a Provinciall Councell, and in every Countie a Countie Councell; the Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Councell to be compoſed of the number of two of each Countie, and the ſaid Provinciall Councell ſhall chooſe a Preſident of themſelves.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That the Provinciall Councell ſhall ſit foure times a yeare, and oftner if there be cauſe for it; that they ſhall have power and authoritie to renew or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe the Judgements of the County counſels, the partie complaining entring ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity <hi>(de adjudicant ſeluendum)</hi> and ſhall, during the troubles, have power to heare and determine all matters of the Crown as Judges of Oyer and Terminer, Jayle Delivery, were wont to do; ſo that no ſpeciall perſon be preſent at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining of matters of blood, and ſhall have power to heare and determine all Civill cauſes, and to eſtabliſh rents, poſſeſſions, ſo they meddle not with Tithe of land other then in caſe of Dower or Joynture; and the Sheriffes Provinciall Generals, and all Commanders of the Armies in caſe of diſobedience are reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively required to execute their Decrees and Orders: and in caſe of debts and Accounts, great conſideration is to be had of the diſabilitie of Creditors occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the warre.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Item,</hi> in every Countie there ſhall be a County Counſell conſiſting of one or two of each Barrony at the election of the County; and where there are no Barronies, the Counſell of ſuch Countie to be of the number of 12. and the ſaid Countie Counſell ſhall have power and authoritie in all points of Juſtices of the Peace to hear and determine all matters concerning the offices of Juſtice of Peace, and all matters of the Crown, hapning within every ſuch County; and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent being a Free, holder may, if he pleaſe, have his triall in the Province, and heare and determine debts, treſpaſſes, and perſonall demands, and to do all things as Juſtices of the Peace were accuſtomed for to do, and to reſtore and eſtabliſh poſſeſſions taken by force or fraud ſince theſe troubles. And likewiſe to take a ſpeciall care that Tenants Farmers be kept to their Farmes where they were uſed, and to be preſerved from extortion and oppreſſion; and that Trades, Tradeſmen, Manufactures, Agritculture and husbandry be maintained, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets daily kept.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Item,</hi> In every County there ſhall be Coroners, high Sheriffes, high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, petty Conſtables, and Goaler, who are to do their reſpective offices as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed; the high Sheriffe to be confirmed or nominated by the ſupreame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111052:2"/>Counſell out of 3. to be preſented by the Counſell and high Sheriffe, is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to execute the commands, Orders, and Decrees of the Provinciall and Countie Councell.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Item,</hi> In Cities and Towns corporate, Juſtice is to be done, and the Laws executed as accuſtomed.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Item,</hi> In every Countie the high Sheriffe ſhall be Proveſt Marſhall, and ſhall have power to execute a Layman not worth 5. l. and none other, for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, manſlaughter, burglary, thefts, robbery, or other capitall offence. Provided the perſon to be executed may have 24. houres times to prepare his ſoule, and that the ſupreame Councell or Provinciall Councell ſhall and may name more Proveſt Martia's as they ſhall think expedient, qualified with the like authority.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered, that no temporall government or juriſdiction ſhall be aſſumed, kept, or exerciſed in this Kingdome, or within any Countie or Province thereof during theſe troubles, other then as is before expreſſed, except ſuch juriſdiction and government as is or ſhall be approved by this generall Aſſembly, or the ſupreame Councell.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered, that whoſoever hath entred ſince the 1. of Octob. 1641. or ſhall hereafter during the continuance of the warre in this Kingdome, enter into the lands, tenements, or hereditaments of any perſon or perſons, who hath been in poſſeſſion of ſuch lands, tenements, or hereditaments, at, or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before the 18 day of Octob either by himſelf or his under tenants, or by the renewing the rents, iſſu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, or profits thereof, ſhall immediately upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand reſtore the ſaid poſſeſſion to the partie or parties ſo put out, with ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable damages as the Councell Provinciall or ſupreame Councell ſhall think fit; or if the partie refuſe to reſtore the ſaid poſſeſſion gained as aforeſaid, upon demand of the partie ſo put out, his heires or aſſignes made to the ſaid poſſeſſor his ſervants or adherents in the premiſſes or publication of this Order, within the Pariſh where ſuch lands lieth, that upon his or their denyall thereof, or default therein, he, his heires and aſſignes ſhall be for ever after debarred and ſecluded from all and every right, title, intereſt, and demand, which he or they may make or pretend to all or any the ſaid lands, tenements, or hereditaments, and if after ſuch deniall or default made, the ſaid partie his heires or aſſignes ſhall not immediately reſtore the poſſeſſion of the ſaid lands, tenements and hereditaments to the party grieved, his heires or aſſignes that he, and they, and his and their adherents in the premiſſes ſhall be declared and proceeded with as enemies. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and ſo it is meant, that if any of the ſaid parties ſo put out, and be declared a neuter or enemy by the Provinciall and ſupreme Councell, that the partie who gained the poſſeſſion as aforeſaid, ſhall give up the poſſeſſion to ſuch perſon or perſons as ſhall be named either by the ſaid County Provinciall or ſupreame Councell, to be diſpoſed of towards the maintenance of the generall cauſe, upon the paine and penaltie aforeſaid; And as for the rents and main profits of the ſaid lands, tenements, and hereditaments, and all kind of rents, and the goods and chattels taken or detained from any Catholique as aforeſaid, due ſatisfaction is to be made of the ſame to the parties from whom the ſame goods, rents, or chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels were or ſhall be taken or beſtowed, ſince theſe troubles began, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111052:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>councell or countie councell ſhall reſpectively order.</p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, for the removall of evill diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and enmitie, and to the end that all men may bend their thoughts and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the common cauſe, that all poſſeſſions of lands and tenements ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and remaine unto ſuch as have already joyned in this union, as they have been for three yeers paſt next before the beginning of theſe troubles, and that no title of land ſhall be drawn into any debate or queſtion untill the next Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, other then in caſe of Mortgages, Leaſes, and particular eſtates, <hi>de facto,</hi> determined or determinated by effluction or other determination thereof.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Item,</hi> For the avoiding Nationall diſtinction between the Subjects of His Majeſties Dominions, which this Aſſembly doth utterly deteſt and abhorre, and which ought not to be endured in a well governed Common-wealth, it is ordered and eſtabliſhed, that on paine of the higheſt puniſhment which may be inflicted by the authoritie of this preſent Aſſembly, that every Romane Catholique, as well Engliſh, Welſh, or Scots, who was of that profeſſion before theſe troubles, and who will come and pleaſe to reſide in this Kingdom, and joyne in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Union, ſhall be preſerved and cheriſhed in his life, goods, and eſtates, by the power, authority and force, if need require, of all the Catholiques of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as full and freely as any native born therein, and ſhall be acquitted and eaſed of one third part in 3. parts to be divided, of publique charges and leavies raiſed, or to be raiſed for the maintenance of this holy warre.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that there ſhall be no diſtinction or compariſon betwixt old Iriſh and old or new Engliſh; or betwixt ſexe or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, or betwixt Citizens or Townſmen and countreymen joyning in this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, upon paine of the higheſt puniſhment that can be inflicted by any of the Counſell aforeſaid, according to the nature and qualitie of the offence and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion like to ſpring from thence.</p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that all new converts born in any of His Majeſties Dominions, or elſe where without manifeſt occaſion given by the perſons converted to the coritry and joyning in this cauſe, ſhall be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Catholiques and natives to all intents and purpoſes.</p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that all the Artificers, Artians, Navigators and Marriners, not being denizons, who ſhall pleaſe to reſide in this Kingdom, ſhall during their reſidence in this Kingdom, after ſuch time as they and their families ſhall be here ſetled, have and enjoy the free liberties and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of nature in all reſpects.</p>
            <p n="20">20. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that in regard of the preſent eſtate and condition of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> no native of this Kingdome; eſpecially if he be a Catholique, or any other Catholique, is permitted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Innes of Court: And to the end the laudible Laws of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> may not die amidſt the diſaſters of theſe times, one Inne of Court ſhall be erected in ſuch place of the Kingdome, as to the ſupreame ſhall be thought fit for the training of the Gentry of the Kingdom to the knowledge of theſe Laws.</p>
            <p n="21">21. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, for the advancement of learning,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111052:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>that in every Province in this Kingdom, Free-Schools ſhall be erected and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſo many and in ſuch places, and in ſuch manner and forme, as to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane and Ordinary of the Dioceſſe in their reſpective Provinces ſhall be thought fit.</p>
            <p n="22">22. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that no Lord, Gentleman, or other perſon, ſhall raiſe or keep any company of ſouldiers, but ſuch as ſhall be authoriſed by the ſupreame Councell, Provinciall Councell, or County Councell, or Magiſtrate within their own corporate Towns. And that the Statutes againſt Seſſe Coynees, or Livery be duely put in execution: and that no company of ſouldiers whatſoever ſhall be payed or relieved by the countrey, excepting ſuch as are or ſhall be enrolled in the Martials Liſts; and none ſhall be billited but by the Conſtable.</p>
            <p n="23">23. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that Church-lands and tithes, impropriate in the hands of Catholique owners before theſe troubles, &amp; joyning in this cauſe, may be left to them according to their ſeverall eſtates, untill the ſame be diſpoſed of by Parliament, they in the intrim anſwering their rents as accuſtomed.</p>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that the Kings cuſtomes, rents, revenewes, arreares and dues, and the rents, iſſues, and profits of the lands, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments, and goods and chattels of the enemies, which are or ſhall be declared by the Provinciall or Supreame Counſell, or by the generall Aſſembly, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and collected and be diſpoſed for his Majeſties uſe and ſervice.</p>
            <p n="25">25. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further ordered and eſtabliſhed, that in every Countie there be Collectors and Receivers to be appointed by the Countie Counſell, and that they be accountable to the ſaid County Counſell for the ſame, which Countie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſhall be accountable to the Provinciall therein halfe yearely, and Provinciall Counſell to the Supreame Councell yearely, to the end the ſame may not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed or unſupplyed.</p>
            <p n="26">26. <hi>Item,</hi> It is ordered and agreed, that where any Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dignitary, or any other perſon or perſons whatſoever, hath or enjoyed any lands, tenements, or hereditaments, tythes, or Church-livings in one Countie or Province, or doth or ſhall keepe his or their reſidence in another Countie or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, or hath his or their relation or nomination in another Countie or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, that in all ſuch caſes the profits accrewing out of all ſuch lands, tenements, or hereditaments, tythes, or Church-livings, to the generall uſe, ſhall be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſaid Countie and Province where the ſaid lands, tenements, and heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments, tythes, or Church-livings doe lye, as by the ſeverall Countie Counſell reſpectively ſhall be thought fit for the publique cauſe.</p>
            <p n="27">27. <hi>Item,</hi> It is ordered and eſtabliſhed by the ſaid Generall Aſſembly, that any woman being a Romane Catholique, and wife of any Proteſtant or Catholique that hath forſaken his houſes, eſtate and wife, and adhere unto the enemy, that every ſuch wife may enter into her Joynture, if any be conveyed unto her, or may recover her thirds of her ſaid husbands eſtate, as if her ſaid husband were actually dead, and that every ſuch wife ſhall be in ſuch condition or capacitie to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111052:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuc and be impleaded, as if her ſhid husband had exiled or abjured the Realme by Judgement of Law, except the Provinciall or Supreame Councell in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar caſes order the contrary.</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Item,</hi> It is ordered and eſtabliſhed, that the poſſeſſion of Proteſtants, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Dignitaties, and Parſons; in the right of their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Churches, or their tenements in the beginning of theſe troubles, ſhall be deemed, taken and conſtrued as the then poſſeſſion of the Catholique Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Dignitaties, Paſtors, and their Tenants reſpectively; to all intents and purpoſes, and that thoſe poſſeſſions are intended within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent order for ſettlement of poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p n="29">29. <hi>Item,</hi> It is ordered and eſtabliſhed, that no man being priſoner by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of any the Councells aforeſaid, ſhall be enlarged without the order of the ſaid Councells, reſpectively; and that no Protection be given to ſervants or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men of the enemies partie, without the like order of the chiefe Commander of the Armie in the ſeverall Provinces or Counties.</p>
            <p n="30">30. <hi>Item,</hi> That whereas abuſes have been committed in ſome parts of this Kingdome, in taking of Armes, Ammunition, and other Merchandiſes from ſeverall Merchants arrived in Creekes or Harbours, farre from their intended Port. By reaſon of Tempeſt, or the danger of the enemy, to the great diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the Merchants; it is therefore ordered and eſtabliſhed, that where any Ship or Shippes, or other Veſſell, ſhall come or arrive in any Harbour, Key, or Creeke, within this Kingdome, Loaden with Armes, Ammunition, or other Merchandiſes, that in ſuch Caſes all thoſe who are or ſhall be in Command in the adjacent Counties reſpectively, ſhall protect and defend the ſaid Merchants, their goods and ſervants, and ſhall at the charges of the ſaid Merchants, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure carriage for the ſaid goods, and ſafely convey the ſame to the ſaid Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants intended Port, and not to ſuffer the ſame, or any of the ſame, under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of paying for the ſame, or otherwiſe to be diſpoſed of or taken before the ſame come to the intended Port, and be entered into the Liſts of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, or the expreſſe direction or writing of the ſaid Commiſſioners; any that ſhall rob, ſteale, or violently take away any of the ſaid goods, contrary to this order, ſhall be deemed and puniſhed as enemies to the publique good of this Kingdome, and ſuffer death therefore.</p>
            <p n="31">31. That certain Commiſſioners ſhall be appertained in every Port Towne of the Freemen and Reſidents therein, by the Provinciall or ſupreame Councell, for the viewing of all the Armes and Ammunition that ſhall be hereafter impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into this Realme from beyond the Seas, and to certifie the ſame to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Councell with all ſpeed; and to prevent abuſes in the ſale, or iſſuing, or diſpoſing of them.</p>
            <p n="32">32. <hi>Item,</hi> It is ordered and eſtabliſhed, that where ſouldiers do run from other Garriſons or Commanders unto other countreys and Provinces; That the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders or chief Governours of the ſaid County or Province, upon complaint made thereof, ſhall ſend back the ſaid fugitive ſouldiers to their Commanders, to be dealt with according to juſtice.</p>
            <p n="33">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111052:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 33. <hi>Item,</hi> It is ordered and eſtabliſhed, that the debts and other duties owing to creditors of this Union, being Neuters and Enemies, ſhall be payed out of the goods, lands, tenements and hereditaments of the ſaid Neuters and Enemies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, before any other publique charge be anſwered thereout.</p>
            <p n="34">34. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and eſtabliſhed, that no ſouldiers or other perſons without command from the county counſell, meddle with the goods or lands of Neuters or Enemies.</p>
            <p n="35">35, <hi>Item,</hi> It is ordered and eſtabliſhed, that to prevent the ſpringing up of all Nationall diſtinctions, the Oath of aſſociation Union be taken ſolemnly after confeſſion, and receiving the Sacrament in the Pariſh churches throughout the Kingdome; and the names of all the perſons of ranke and qualitie in every Pariſh that takes the ſame be enrolled in parchment, and be returned, ſigned and ſealed by the Pariſh Prieſt, to the Ordinatie of every Dioceſſe, who is to keep the ſame in his Treaſurie, and to certifie a copie thereof under ſeale to the Metropolitane; who is to keep that, and to certifie a true copy thereof under his Metropoliticall ſeale, to the Rolls of the Kingdom, where the ſame is to be enrolled.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. P.</hi> and <hi>M. S.</hi> in <hi>Goldſmiths</hi>-Alley. 1643. <hi>March</hi> the ſixt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
